Guide to the Charles Owen Rice Papers, 1894-2005 AIS.1976.11
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Charles Owen Rice Papers
1894-2005
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Rice, Charles Owen
AIS.1976.11
55.24 Linear Feet (51boxes, 4 oversize folders, 1 film)
Charles Owen Rice was a Roman Catholic priest who was active in the Pittsburgh community as well as national labor and civil rights movements. He was involved as a journalist, as director of the Catholic Radical Alliance of Pittsburgh, as one of the founders and first chairman of the Pittsburgh Chapter of the Association of Catholic Trade Unionists (ACTU), and as founder of St. Joseph's House of Hospitality (Pittsburgh). The collection includes correspondence, subject files, transcripts of radio broadcasts, manuscripts, case files, family papers, audiotapes, photographs and a film.
Biography
Msgr. Charles Owen Rice was born in New York City in 1908, the son of Irish immigrants. After his mother died when he was four, he and a brother were sent back to Ireland to be raised by an aging grandmother. By age 11, he returned to the states and was ordained into the priesthood in 1934 following studies at Duquesne University and St. Vincent Seminary, both in Pittsburgh. After ordination in 1934, he became involved with labor unions, often acting as an arbitrator. He was a leader in resisting the influence of the Communists in labor unions in the 1930s and 1940s. Partially in response to the Communist effort to control organized labor, Father Rice aided in founding the Association of Catholic Trade Unionists; he also served as its chaplain.
In 1937 Rice founded St. Joseph's House of Hospitality, giving shelter and food to homeless men in the Hill District of Pittsburgh. Labor, Communism, and St. Joseph's House were frequent topics on his weekly radio program which aired from 1937 to 1969. He and two older clergy also organized the Catholic Radical Alliance, which later became an important adjunct of the Catholic Worker movement in America. During World War II, Father Rice was appointed local rent director of the Hill District.
In 1952 Father Rice received a pastorate appointment in Natrona and later Washington, Pa., but continued his interests in labor. He walked picket lines with countless unions, protested steel plant shutdowns in the 1980s, and joined The Pittsburgh Press strikers in 1992. Although long interested in civil rights, his appointment to the predominantly African American parish of Holy Rosary in Pittsburgh's Homewood section kindled greater interest in the cause. He later became a critic of the Vietnam War. In his seven decades as a priest, Rice was pastor of numerous churches, including St. Joseph's in Natrona, Immaculate Conception in Washington, Pa., Holy Rosary in Homewood, and St. Ann's in Castle Shannon, Pa.
Father Rice passed away in 2005.
Arrangement
The collection is comprised of 12 series:
Series I. Subject Files
Series II. Correspondence
Series III. Radio Broadcasts
Series IV. Arbitration Cases
Series V. FBI Files
Series VI. Holy Rosary School
Series VII. Manuscripts and Publications
Series VIII. Autobiographical Material
Series IX. Family Papers
Series X. Photographs
Series XI. Audio Tapes
Scope and Content Notes
The Charles Owen Rice Papers include correspondence, subject files, transcripts of Rice's radio broadcasts, manuscripts of published and unpublished writings, arbitration case files, family papers, audio tapes, photographs, and a copy of the film Humble Greatness: The Life of Philip Murray, which he narrated. The collection also includes material relating to labor, labor associations, organizations, and societies, the labor union movement, industrial unionism, strikes, politics and government, social welfare, civil rights, prison reform, the peace movement, Vietnam War protests, draft resistance, Communism, Communist leadership, Communist influence in the labor movement, anticommunism, Association of Catholic Trade Unionists and the Pittsburgh Chapter, Catholic Radical Alliance of Pittsburgh, St. Joseph's House of Hospitality (Pittsburgh), Steel Workers Organizing Committee, United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America, and Philip Murray.
Access Restrictions
Individual Prisoners' Case Files, Correspondence, and other prisoner information from the Prison Society of Southwest Pennsylvania (Boxes 14-16) are closed until the prisoner's death, unless written permission is provided by the prisoner.
Accruals
Additional material was donated by Charles McCollester and Geraldine A. Mullooly in August 2006. In July 2011 Steve Rosswurm donated the files he obtained in 2009 as a result of a Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) request pertaining to FBI files.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Monsignor Charles Owen Rice in 1976 and 1989.
Previous Citation
Charles Owen Rice Papers, 1935-1998, AIS.1976.11, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Labor -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Arbitration, Industrial -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Steel industry and trade -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Propaganda, Anti-communist -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Draft resisters -- United States; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements; Peace movements -- United States; Civil rights -- United States; Charities -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Strikes and lockouts -- Steel industry and trade -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Electric industry workers -- Labor unions -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Education; Iron and steel workers -- Labor unions -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Social action; Labor movement -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pennsylvania -- Church history; Societies; Prisons -- United States; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Politics and government; Personal papers; Labor; Steel industry and trade -- Pennsylvania; Catholic Church -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Clergy; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- Pennsylvania; Societies -- Pennsylvania; Pennsylvania -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Religion; Pennsylvania -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Church history; Societies -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Clergy -- Pennsylvania; Labor leaders -- Pennsylvania; Journalists -- Pennsylvania; Priests; Transcripts; Association of Catholic Trade Unionists. Pittsburgh Chapter; Association of Catholic Trade Unionists; Rice, Charles Owen; Murray, Philip
- Subject Files, 1894-2005; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I consists of a subject file that was created and used by Father Rice for the greater part of his career. Personal names, events and organizations are located within these files. This series contains articles, newsclippings, correspondence, pamphlets, and reports and are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Abortion, 1970-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    See Also
    American Civil Liberties Union--Abortion, Birthright
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Action Housing, 1964-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Forward, Housing
  - Adult Education, 1951-1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Afro-Asian Freedom Rally, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Agitator, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Allegheny County Board of Health, 1985-1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Allegheny County Prison Board, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Aluminum Workers, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Amalgamated Food Employees Union, Local 590, 1941-1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Amalgamated Food Employees Union, Local 590, News, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Amalgamated Food Employees Union, Local 590, News, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Amalgamated Food Employees Union, Local 590, News, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Amalgamated Food Employees Union, Local 590, News, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Amalgamated Food Employees Union, Local 590, News, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Amalgamated Food Employees Union, Local 590, News, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Amalgamated Food Employees Union, Local 590, News, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Amalgamated Meat Cutters and Butcher Workmen of North America, 1951-1956 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - America-National Catholic Weekly, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - American Cancer Society, Washington County Unit, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, 1966-1973 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, Minutes, 1966-1974 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, Abortion, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - American Committee for Peace and Justice, 1937-1941 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - American Federation of Radio and Television Artists, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - American Newspaper Guild, 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - American Service Institute of Allegheny County, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - American Thermoplastic Co., 1967-1975 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Americans for Democratic Action, 1963-1975 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Anti-Catholicism, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Anti-Catholicism, Knights of Columbus "oath", 1960 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Anti Catholic Publications, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Anti-Semitism, 1938-1945 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Another Side, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Arabs, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Archdiocese of St. Paul and Minneapolis, Priests' Retreat, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Archives of Industrial Society, University of Pgh., 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Argentina, 1964-1973 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Association for Legal Justice, Ireland, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Association for Union Democracy, 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Association of Catholic Trade Unionists, Camden Chapter, 1951-1956 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Association of Catholic Trade Unionists, Catholic Radical Alliance, 1937-1937 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Association of Catholic Trade Unionists, Cleveland Convention, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Association of Catholic Trade Unionists, Committee Breakfast, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Association of Catholic Trade Unionists, Correspondence, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Association of Catholic Trade Unionists, Correspondence, 1939-1941, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Association of Catholic Trade Unionists, National Conventions, 1941-1950 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Association of Catholic Trade Unionists, National Executive Board Meeting, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Association of Catholic Trade Unionists, National Office, 1939-1941 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Association of Catholic Trade Unionists, News Releases, 1938-1941 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Association of Catholic Trade Unionists, News Releases, 1941-1949 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Association of Catholic Trade Unionists, Pamphlets, 1939-1949 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Association of Catholic Trade Unionists, Pittsburgh Chapter, 1939-1941 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Association of Catholic Trade Unionists, Resolutions, 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Association of Catholic Trade Unionists, Roddy Dissertation, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Association of Catholic Trade Unionists, United Electrical Workers, 1933-1939 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Association of Catholic Trade Unionists, Workers School, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Association of Community Organizations for Reform Now, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Association of Pittsburgh Priests, 1967-1976 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Automation, 1959-1962 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Automation, 1959-1962 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Automation, 1959-1962 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Automation, 1959-1962 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Ball Trial, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Battle of Homestead Foundation (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Bell Telephone Strike, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Bellurgan Church, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Biafra Relief, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Biographies, General Articles on Charles Owen Rice, 1941-1974 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Birth Control, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Birthright of Pittsburgh, Inc., 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Black Dispatch, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Black, Gregory D. "Catholics, the Catholic Press and Communism", 1991 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Blair, Frederick, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Bolts, Brother William, "Pittsburgh's Labor Priest in the 1930s", 1973 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Books Referring to Charles Owen Rice, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Boyle, Bishop, 1937-1948 (Box 2, Folder 34a)
  - Boyle, W. A. "Tony", 1969-1978 (Box 2, Folder 34b)
  - Bridges, Harry, Trial, 1941-1944 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Bridget Lee, Religious and Charitable Trust, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Brother Dan's Searchlight, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Browning Ferris Industries and Giant Eagle Strikes, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Business Education Day, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Canonsburg Hospital Strike, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Capital Punishment, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Capital Punishment, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Capital Punishment, Controversy in Congressional Digest, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Capital Punishment, General Correspondence, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Capital Punishment, News Clippings, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Capital Punishment, Opinions, The United States Law Week, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Capital Punishment, Pennsylvania Catholic Conference, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Capital Punishment, Positions Pro and Con, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Capital Punishment, Publications, 1967-1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Capital Punishment, Testimony before the Governor's Study Commission, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Cardamore, Tom, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Carlow Books, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Cassella, John James, "Silver Jubilee Mass", 1983 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Castle Shannon Police, Grievances, 1977-1984 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Castle Shannon Police, Pension, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Catholic Actions Federation, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Catholic Campaigners for Christ, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Catholic Charities, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Catholic Clergy Conference on International Apostolate, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Catholic Diocese of Pittsburgh, "We Are Called, A Musical Celebration", 1993 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Catholic Industrial Congress, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Catholic Interracial Council, 1966-1968, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Catholic Radical Alliance, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Catholic Radical Alliance, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    American Committee for Peace and Justice
  - Catholic Radical Alliance, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Catholic Radical Alliance, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - "Catholic Radical Alliance" Paper, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Catholic Social Service, 1951-1956 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Catholic Social Service, 1960-1965 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Catholic Social Service, Adoption, 1959-1965 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Celebration (Homily), 1975 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Central Medical Pavilion, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Chamber of Commerce, Labor, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Chamber of Commerce, Washington, Pa., 1960-1964 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Chancery Personnel Building, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Charity Appeals, 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Chemical Workers, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Child Welfare League of Pittsburgh Report, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Chile, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Chimbote, Peru, Fulbright Scholar, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Christian Democratic Union of Central Europe, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - The Christian Front, 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Christmas List, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Chrysler, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Church and State Separation, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Agenda, 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Church Allocation Requests, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Church Profiles, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Church Profiles, Friendship Park, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Church Profiles, Friendship Park, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Church Profiles, Friendship Park, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Church Profiles, Friendship Park, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Consultation on Churches in Older Communities, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Correspondence, 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Financial Statements, 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Information Survey Forms, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Inner City Church, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Interfaith Housing, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Minutes of the Board, 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Minutes of the Executive Committee, 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Miscellaneous Reports, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Monongahela Valley Area, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, North Side Church Planning Study, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, North Side Church Planning Study, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, North Side Church Planning Study, Proposals for Protestant Churches, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, North Side Church Planning Study, Proposal for Roman Catholic Church, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, North Side Church Planning Study, Existing Conditions, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Oakland Churches and Services Building, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Oakland Ministries, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Policies, Amendments, and Agreements, undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Recommendations and Proposals, undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Schedule of Meetings, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Church Planning Board of Southwestern Pennsylvania, Staff Reports, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Ciletti, Linda Joy, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Citizens Against Slum Housing, 1961-1967 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Citizens Conference on State Legislation, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Civil Defense, 1961-1965 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Civil Disorders, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Civil Liberties, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Civil Rights Committee, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Clark Candy Company Boycott, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Clearing House for Occupancy Selections, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Cleland, Dr Hugh G, 1956-1961 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Clergy Conversation Group, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Clergy Council, Diocese of Pittsburgh, 1969-1974 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Cleveland Little Steel Strike, 1937, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Clothing Workers, 1947-1951 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Coal Miners, 1978, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Cobucci, Dolores, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Commentator, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Committee for Industrial Organization and American Federation of Labor Information, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Committee for Industrial Organization and American Federation of Labor Information, undated (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Committee for Inter-American Cooperation, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Committee for Liturgical Life, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Committee of Catholic Charities, 1960-1962 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Committee Urging Racial Equality, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Communism, Hudson Debate, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Communism, Johnson Indictment, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Communism, Labor Movements, 1947-1950 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Communism, Labor Movements, 1947-1950 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Communism, Labor Movements, 1947-1950 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Communism, Meyers, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Communism, Miscellaneous, 1937-1941 and undated (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Communism, North Side Riot, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Community Chest, Washington, Pa., 1960 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Community Chest, Washington, Pa, 1960-1964 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Community Chest, Washington, Pa., Donor List, 1963-1965 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Community Welfare Fund, 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Concerned Clergy of Squirrel Hill, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Conferences, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Congress, Correspondence with Members of, 1941-1942 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Conscientious Objection, 1967-1970 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Conscientious Objection, Catholics, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Consumer Protection, Pennsylvania, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Coordinating Committee on Employment, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Correctional Services Association, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Corrections, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Costello Publishing v. John E. Rotelle v. Episcopal Conference of Australia, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Coughlin, Father Charles E., 1966-1974 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    United Auto Workers
  - Crank Mail, 1941-1942, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - The Critic, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Cuba Trip, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - The Daily Worker Communist Newspaper, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - The Daily Worker Communist Newspaper, 1947-1949 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Dairy Industry Association, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Darby, Reverend Thomas, Correspondence, 1945-1946 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Day, Dorothy, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Deardon, Bishop John F., Correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Death Penalty, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Defend America, Committee to, 1940-1941 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Democratic Party National Convention, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Department Store Workers, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Diocesan and Clergy Affairs, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Diocesan Commission for Catholic Charities and Social Welfare (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Diocesan Commission for Catholic Charities and Social Welfare, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Diocesan Commission for Catholic Charities and Social Welfare, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Diocesan Commission for Catholic Charities and Social Welfare, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Diocesan Commission for Catholic Charities and Social Welfare, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Diocese of Pittsburgh, Office of Economic Opportunity Program, 1965-1969 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Diocese of Pittsburgh, Task Force, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Diocese of Pittsburgh, Teacher Contract Forms, undated (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Diocese of Pittsburgh, Urban Task Force, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Disappointed Americans, Committee on, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Dog, Father Rice's, 1955-1958 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Draft Protest, undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Drugs, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Dubois Clubs, 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Duffy, John, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Duquesne Light Strike, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Duquesne University, undated (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Duquesne University, Institute of Labor Relations, 1945-1947 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Duquesne University, Institute of Labor Relations, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Duquesne University Labor Institute, 1946-1947, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Duquesne University, Management and Labor Relations, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Duquesne University Release Concerning Labor Relations, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - East End Cooperative Ministry, 1987-1990 (Box 6, Folder 1)